Guide to the St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio records, 1950-1998 MS2004
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio records
1950-1998
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2004
16 Linear Feet
The St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio Records collection contains founding documents, historical background information, articles, essays, speeches, lectures, choreography notes, teaching notes, notebooks, clippings, reviews, press releases, advertisements, brochures, fliers, budgets, accountings, tax records, programs, schedules, repertoires, audiotapes, videotapes, legal documents, photographs, negatives, slides, correspondence, minutes, annual reports, financial reports, funding proposals and applications, agreements, contracts, resumes, and lists.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Mary Craighill and Jim Adams, Rector of St. Mark's Episcopal Church, Capitol Hill donated the St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio collection to the Gelman Library in March of 1995 for inclusion in the Dance Archives of the Greater Washington Region.
Upon donation of the collection, Mary Craighill and Jim Adams transferred all right, title, and interest in and to the materials of the collection.
Historical or Biographical Note
The history of St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio follows the chronicle of the career of Mary Craighill. Craighill has performed, choreographed, and taught dance in the Washington area since 1950. In some sense, the Company began in 1950 as a duet between Craighill and Mildred Lachman who were both dancers with Erika Thimey's performing group at the time. They were soon joined by Robert Fabik. The trio's repertoire was composed largely of abstract or comic works. In 1953, Louis Tupler replaced Fabick and the trio became a serious company. In addition to her performances with the trio, Craighill directed several special programs in the Washington area and in 1956 opened a studio in her home in McLean, Virginia. Around 1955, Craighill and Tupler formed and directed the Washington Contemporary Dance Group. In 1957, friends of the WCDG formed a supporting organization known as the Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc.
In these early years, Craighill began to explore the use of dance as communication and as an expression of religion. The appearances of the trio and the WCDG at local theatres and events provided Craighill with testing grounds for these dance themes. By 1959 she and Tupler had developed their own special interests in dance that ceased to compliment the other's. Craighill formed the Mary Craighill Dance Company and continued to enjoy the support of the WCDF, Inc as she concentrated her efforts on the challenge of religious dance. Her group accepted an invitation to join the Chancel Drama Cycle, an inter-denominational consortium of drama groups presenting secular plays during lent, and toured the Washington area and the East Coast as its only dance member.
St. Mark's Episcopal Church invited Craighill and her group to become the dance company in residence in 1962. The group became known as the St. Mark's Chancel Dance Group. The St. Mark's Dance Studio was opened upstairs in the church in 1963. Then, as now, both the company and the studio had the encouragement and support of the church and were free of artistic interference. The groupe strived to express themselves through Ballet, modern, jazz, ethnic and even mime. A striving for simultaneous inreach and outreach has guided the company. Efforts to reestablish dance as an acceptable medium of religious expression of the liturgy of the church has constituted the "inreach". The company's "outreach" has been to the marketplace where they have tried to present valuable, substantial dances of integrity that are meaningful to the modern human being.
Throughout the sixties the company's repertoire strengthened and matured. In 1965 they were a semi-professional company as recognized by the District of Columbia Arts Commission. This gave the company temporary strength and stability and the opportunity to compete with other companies. The company began a series of performances in DC public schools in the late sixties and gave performances and workshops to the general public as well. The St. Mark's Junior Company formed in 1968 for pre professionals ages nine and up from the studio. The St. Mark's Dance Company (senior), which performed nationally and internationally as professionals, was disband temporarily due to financial difficulty. The need for full-time, full-salaried dancers became more apparent than ever. Funding from the Sears-Roebuck Foundation for a lecture-demonstration series came in 1969 and was funded for a second year. The company was located in Arlington county from 1971-1975 as the dance company in residence. They toured Arlington schools and Virginia state. Mary Craighill created the curricula for Arlington schools. As the Arlington-St. Mark's Dance Company (also known as the Arlington Dance Theatre), they were a company of professional status and capacity. Craighill developed curricula and standards for all county sponsored dance teaching in Arlington county. Previous activities with St. Mark's continued during this time.
Arlington county provided financial resources but not the support and artistic freedom that St. Mark's provided. Craighill returned to St. Mark's full-time in 1975. During that same year the Company began a series of performances called Lunch Theatre. Monthly lunch hour performances by the St. Mark's Dance Company and other DC performing artists continued for 5 ½ years with support from the District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities and the National Endowment for the Arts, Expansion Arts Division. By 1981 Lunch Theatre had proved itself too costly in terms of money, artistic energy and time. It was discontinued and Craighill and the Company turned their full attention to the philosophy of inreach-outreach. During the eighties, liturgies in dance were choreographed for the church, public performances were given, and an outreach program focusing on institutions such as veteran hospitals, retirement homes, and shelters developed. Since 1990 both commissioned work for St. Mark's services and secular dances have been a large portion of the Company's work. The St. Mark's Dance Company continues through its versatile and eclectic approach to technique to make a significant and unique contribution to the city of Washington.
Collection Scope and Content
The St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio Records collection contains founding documents, historical background information, articles, essays, speeches, lectures, choreography notes, teaching notes, notebooks, clippings, reviews, press releases, advertisements, brochures, fliers, budgets, accountings, tax records, programs, schedules, repertoires, audiotapes, videotapes, legal documents, photographs, negatives, slides, correspondence, minutes, annual reports, financial reports, funding proposals and applications, agreements, contracts, resumes, and lists.
The collection, dating from 1950 to 1998, presents a view of the history and workings of the St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, with founder Mary Craighill as director, and their impact upon the Capitol Hill community as well as upon the Greater Washington area. The collection also provides valuable insight into the background, meaning, and scope of religious dance. One strength of the collection is the cohesion lent by the presence of many of Mary Craighill's personal documents throughout the collection. As an especially dedicated dance artist, Craighill's business, art, religion, and personal affairs intertwined. The great variety of activities and changes of the Company are better understood through Craighill's goals and aspirations as she was the one constant in the life of the Company.
Collection Organization
Organized into 5 series: Administrative records; Performances, programs, and special events files; Miscellaneous files; Non-print media; and Oversized records.
Photographs; Color slides; Washington (D.C.); Audiotapes; Ballet; Dance companies; Dance; Thimey, Erika; St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio; Craighill, Mary
- Administrative records, 1950-1992; MS2004 Series 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The materials in this series date from 1950 to 1992 and are arranged chronologically. There is historical background information, including founding documents, articles/essays, and general historical background and administrative boards and committees records, consisting of minutes from board meetings, board member's correspondence and memoranda, annual reports, and meeting notices. There are correspondence, including business correspondence, personal correspondence to Mary Craighill, photographs, and clippings; some of which are unidentified and undated, as well as financial records of the studio and company's budgets and accountings records, several different receipts and vouchers, correspondence, monthly and annual financial reports, tax records, negatives, and clippings. There are funding proposals and applications, consisting of funding proposals and applications in both draft and final form, and correspondence and personnel records containing contracts, agreements, resumes, applications, audition materials, reports, staff lists, and correspondence. Additionally, there are public relations materials containing clippings, fact sheets and brochures about the company, press releases, announcements, advertisements, reviews and articles about performances, class and company schedules, repertoires, booking information, fliers, newsletters, seasonal information, and essays.
  - Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., Certificate of Incorporation, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., Resolution, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Washington Liturgical Dance Society, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio Historical Background, 1962-1983 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., Resolution, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, Charter, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, Charter, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., 1959-1962 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., n.d., undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Arlington Dance Theatre Board, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1975-1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Lunch Theatre Committee and Publicity Committee, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Board, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: Executive Committee of the St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, 1987-1992 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Administrative Boards and Committees Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Advisory Board, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1959 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1980-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1982-1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, n.d., undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Financial Records: Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., 1956-1963 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1965-1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Financial Records: Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Financial Records: Arlington Dance Theatre, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1983-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1985-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Financial Records: St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Financial Records: unidentified, undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Recreation Department Proposal, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Evaluation Report Form for the Arts Agency, Individual Projects, Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc., 1967 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Taft Proposal, Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc. and St. Mark's Dance Company, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Taft Proposal, Washington Contemporary Dance Foundation, Inc. and St. Mark's Dance Company, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Workshop Series in Dance Proposal, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: A Proposal to Support the Community and Educational Activities of an Inner City Dance Company, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Department of Health, Education, and Welfare and Bureau of Research Proposals, 1969-1971 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Dance in the District of Columbia Public Schools, Title I Proposal, 1970 ca. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Elementary and Secondary Education Act Title III Application, 1970 ca. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Arlington Projects Proposals, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Arlington Projects Proposals, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Gum Springs Program/Learning Through Dance Film Proposal, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Proposals, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Dance Company in Residence (Arlington County) Proposal, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Arlington Dance Theatre Proposal for Thirty-Week Season, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Virginia Commission of the Arts and Humanities Proposal, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Choreography, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Choreography, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Applications, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1977-1978 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Application for Title VI (Comprehensive Employment and Training Act) Funds, 1978 ca. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Proposal for Video Tape Package of A Christmas Carol, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Application, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: City Dance Audition Application, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on Arts and Humanities, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1979-1980 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Booth Ferris Foundation Proposal, Lunch Theatre, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Riverside Dance Festival Applications, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Arts DC Comprehensive Employment and Training Act Worksites, Application, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Dance Notation Bureau Questionnaire, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Mid-Atlantic States Arts Consortium, Inc., Performing Group Application, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: City Dance Audition Application, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Applications, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Applications, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Applications, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Applications, 1980-1982 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Summer Dance Festival at Glen Echo Park Application, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: National Endowment for the Arts Application, Lunch Theatre, 1981-1982 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Proposals to the Vestry of St. Mark's Church, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Special Constituencies Application, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Young Audiences Program Application, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Young Audiences Program Application, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: District of Columbia Commission on the Arts and Humanities Application, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Special Constituencies Program Application, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Outline of Proposal for Partial Funding for Christmas Jazz Workshop, 1987-1988 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Preliminary Draft, Description of Conference on Liturgical Dance, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Champs Foundation Application, 1991-1992 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Funding Proposals and Applications: Unidentified Application, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Personnel Records: Contracts/Agreements, 1960 ca. --1974 ca. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Personnel Records: Resumes/Applications, 1960 ca. --1974 ca. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Personnel Records: Salary Reports, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Personnel Records: Audition Materials, 1971-1974 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Personnel Records: St. Mark's Dance Studio Staff and Teacher Lists, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Personnel Records: Assorted, 1965-1982 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Public Relations: Clippings, Mary Craighill and Washington Contemporary Dance Group, 1950 ca. --1962 ca. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Public Relations: General Information/Fact Sheets, Washington Contemporary Dance Group, 1957-1959 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Public Relations: Brochure, Washington Contemporary Dance Group, 1962 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Public Relations: Clippings, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1962-1963 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Public Relations: Press Releases, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1962-1970 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Public Relations: Announcements and Advertisements, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio and Craighill Studio, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Public Relations: Performance Schedules and Repertoires, St. Mark's Dance Company, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Public Relations: Reviews, St. Mark's Dance Company, 1963-1969 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Public Relations: Class Schedules, St. Mark's Dance Studio and Craighill Studio, 1963-1970 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Public Relations: Season Information, St. Mark's Dance Studio and Craighill Information, 1963-1970 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Public Relations: Brochures, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio and Craighill Studio, 1964 ca. (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Public Relations: Clippings, St. Mark's Church, 1964-1985 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - Public Relations: Articles, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio, 1966-1973 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Public Relations: Newsletter, St. Mark's Dance Company, 1967 May (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Public Relations: Brochures, St. Mark's Dance Company and Studio and Craighill Studio, 1967 ca. --1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Public Relations: Booking Information, St. Mark's Dance Company, 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Public Relations: Reviews, St. mark's Dance Company and Arlington-St. Mark's Dance Company, 1970 ca. --1972 (Box 8, Folder 4)